Alexander F Wall

0457 252 302 alexfwall@gmail.com 🖂



linkedin.com/in/alexfwall researchgate.net/profile/Alexander-Wall-2

Palaeoecologist

Researcher and educator with 15+ years experience. PhD student using pollen, geochemical, and sedimentary proxies to reconstruct past environments. Track record of designing interdisciplinary, independent projects resulting in publications and professional presentations. Educator with extensive experience in formal and informal settings—in classrooms, labs, and the field.

Education

- PhD in Earth and Environmental Sciences. University of Wollongong, expected January 2023
- Master of Science in Geology, University of Cincinnati, August 2016
- Bachelor of Science in Geoscience, University of Iowa. December 2007
- Bachelor of Arts in Philosophy, University of Iowa, December 2007

Competencies

R programming language •

ArcGIS Data Management

Citizen Science - Adobe CS -

Virtual/Class/Field Teaching

Acetolysis Pollen Prep - SDHR27:

Project Management Essentials; ARMS Masterclass: Fundamentals of Project Management;

Unconscious Bias Training; 4WD certifications SISODRV001 and RIIVEH305F; Wilderness First Aid SISSS00126; Introduction to

Radiocarbon dating and Bayesian modelling

Professional Development

ECR Representative for the ARC Centre of Excellence for Biodiversity and Heritage, January 2023-January 2024

Australasian Quaternary Association, Secretary, November 2018-May 2022

GeoQuEST, Seminar Organiser, March 2020-January 2021

Experience

Postdoctoral Fellow School of Culture, History and Language Australian National University. November 2022-Present

Setting up a pollen monitoring network across Australia

PhD Student, Demonstrator, Lab Assistant Earth and Environmental Science, University of Wollongong. August 2018-Present

- PhD project: Reconstruction of Holocene climate and environments of eastern Indonesia
 - ★ Palynological, geochemical, and sedimentological proxies used to reconstruct past environments
 - ★ Compiled, analysed, and visualised data from over 400 published articles for review chapter
- Demonstrated for courses:
 - ★ From the Field to the Lab: Producing your **Ultimate Quaternary Record**
 - ★ Fluvial Geomorphology
 - ★ Planet Earth
- Lab work:
 - ★ Pollen preparation
 - ★ Carbonate preparation for isotope analysis
 - ★ SEM, transmission, cross-polar microscopy

Certificates:

- ✓ Fundamentals of Deep Learning, NVIDIA
- ✓ Remote First Aid, Allens Training Pty Ltd

Short Courses:

- ✓ Indigenous Community Engagement in a Field Setting: Working on Country, CABAH
- ✓ NEOTOMA(TILIA)/OCTOPUS and Pollen Data Analysis, CABAH
- ✓ How to Write for The Conversation, CABAH
- ✓ Species Distribution Modelling 101

Awards:

✓ CABAH Symposium photo competition "Just for Fun" category

Volunteer Work

- The Freedom Hub January 2020—Present
- American Civil Liberties Union June 2017–June 2018
- Nechama disaster response September 2016

Professional Presentations

- wall, AF, Late Quaternary palaeoenvironmental records of tropical Australasia. Talk presented at Australasian Quaternary Association (AQUA) Conference; 23 Jul, 2020; Virtual
- (invited) Wall, AF, Northern Gateway Flagship. Talk presented at CABAH Annual Symposium, 1 Nov, 2020; Virtual
- wall, AF, <u>Late Quaternary</u> palaeoenvironmental records of tropical Australasia. Poster presented at International Quaternary
 Association (INQUA) Conference; 29
 Jul, 2019; Dublin, IE

Experience (cont)

Biology Instructor, Grand View University, Des Moines, IA. *August 2017–April 2018*

Demonstrating for laboratory sections of "Introduction to Biology"

Freelance Proofreader, Proof-Reading-Service.com Ltd, Hertfordshire, UK. *December 2016–August 2017*

Proofread scientific articles and books

Master's Degree Student in Geology, University of Cincinnati. *August 2014–August 2016*

- Thesis project, "Bellwether of the Canaries:
 Anthropogenic effects on the land snail fauna of the
 Canary Islands" Published in Biodiversity and
 Conservation
- Laboratory Assistant preparing carbonate samples for stable isotope analysis
- Field demonstrating: Paleontology, Stratigraphy
- Co-led workshop Quantitative Methods in R

Assistant to the Associate Director for Outreach, Paleontological Research Institution (PRI), Ithaca, NY February 2011–June 2014

- Liaised between PRI and Cornell University on several National Science Foundation-funded projects
- Regional and Local Earth Inquiry: a National Science Foundation (NSF)-funded project providing teacher professional development to secondary school Earth science teachers including conducting workshops, field work, and writing for the Teacher-Friendly Guides to Geology series of books
- Fossil Finders: an NSF-funded project. Collecting, curating, and digitising Devonian fossil specimens; documenting and creating Virtual Field Experience of locality; collecting and analysing data
- Co-Leader, Geological Society of America, Field Trip: Geology along the Rocky Mountain Front Range
- Convened the 2011 and 2012 Summer Symposium
- Training new staff and students to use Institution's scanning electron microscope

- wall, AF, Late Quaternary palaeoenvironmental records of tropical Australasia. Talk presented at Australasian Quaternary Association (AQUA) Conference; 11 Dec, 2018; Canberra, ACT
- wall, AF, <u>Late Quaternary</u> palaeoenvironmental records of tropical Australasia. Poster presented at Australasian Quaternary Association (AQUA) Conference; 11 Dec, 2018; Canberra, ACT

Prof Presentations (cont)

- wall, AF, <u>Taphonomic lag on land: Snail death assemblages show rapid incorporation of synanthropic communities on San Salvador Island.</u>
 The Bahamas. Talk presented at the Geological Society of America's (GSA) 127th Annual Meeting and Exposition; 2015, Nov 3; Baltimore, MD
- Rasmussen, B; Wall, AF, 2015, A quantitative study of bivalves bioeroded by Cliondidae sponges from San Salvador, Bahamas. Talk presented at the Geological Society of America's (GSA) 127th Annual Meeting and Exposition; 3 Nov, 2015; Baltimore, MD
- Wall, AF, Patchy distribution of tree snails of San Salvador, The Bahamas. Talk presented at the 9th annual Ohio (River) Valley Unified Malacologists (OVUM) meeting, 2015, Oct 17; Pittsburgh, PA
- Wall, AF; Dietl, GP, Marginal damage, major consequences: the effects of sublethal damage on the hard clam Mercenaria mercenaria.

Experience (cont)

(Cont) Assistant to the Associate Director for Outreach, Paleontological Research Institution (PRI), Ithaca, NY *February 2011–June 2014*

- Manager and curator of Education Collection of hundreds of fossil, modern, and antique replica specimens
- Research on predation of lightning whelks on hard clams resulting in a talk at the 2013 Geological Society of America conference
- Project managed and led fossil collecting trips and geology-themed walking tours of New York state parks

Collections Intern, Paleontological Research Institution June 2010–February 2011

Curated, catalogued historically significant malacological collections

Teacher, Kojen English Language Schools, Taipei, Taiwan. *June 2008–January 2010*

Wrote lesson plans for and taught preschool classes students learning English as a second language

Collections Assistant, University of Iowa Paleontology Repository, Iowa City, IA. *November 2006–May 2008*

- Digitised type specimens, performed curatorial work, processed specimen loans
- Developed standard procedure for scanning electron microscopy and light photography

Publications

- (in prep) Wall, AF, (expected 2022) Environmental History of Misool. in: D Gaffney & M Ririmasse (eds). Archaeology and Material Culture in Western New Guinea
- Wall, AF; Yanes, Y; Miller, J; and Miller, AI, 2017,

 <u>Bellwether of the Canaries: Anthropogenic effects on the land snail fauna of the Canary Islands.</u> Biodiversity and Conservation.

Talk presented at 8th annual Ohio (River) Valley Unified Malacologists (OVUM) meeting; 2014, Sept 27; Cincinnati, OH

Wall, AF; Dietl, GP, Marginal damage, major consequences: the effects of sublethal damage on the hard clam Mercenaria mercenaria.

Talk presented at the Geological Society of America's (GSA) 125th Anniversary Annual Meeting and Exposition; 2013, Oct 27; Denver, CO

Prof Presentations (cont)

- Duggan-Haas, DA; Kissel, RA; Abbott, LD; Wall, AF; Samuel, J; Ross, RM, The potential to develop and share deep understandings of place through virtual fieldwork and broadcasting from the field. Talk presented at the Geological Society of America's (GSA) 125th Anniversary Annual Meeting and Exposition; 27–30 Oct, 2013; Denver, CO
- Durham, SR; Duggan-Haas, DA; Wall, AF; Kissel, RA; Ross, RM, Virtual fieldwork experiences (VFEs) to bridge the gap between classroom and field-based paleontology education. Talk presented at North American Paleontological Convention; 2014, Gainesville, FL
- Ross, RM; Buckler, CS; Capps, DK; Cronin, KE; Crawford, BA; Smrecak, TA; Wall, AF, Participation of K-12 teachers and students in paleontology: Factors impacting effectiveness and sustainability. Talk presented at North American Paleontological Convention, 2014, Gainesville, FL

Publications (cont)

- Colpaert, C; Nikitenkoa, B; Khafaevab, S; Wall, AF, 2016, The evolution of Late Callovian to Early Kimmeridgian foraminiferal associations from the central part of the Russian Sea (Makar'yev section, Volga River Basin, Russia). Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology
- Wall, AF, 2014, Glaciers of the Midwestern US. pages 107–123, in: MD Lucas, RM Ross, & AN Swaby (eds). The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth Science of the Midwestern US. Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York
- Wall, AF, 2014, Mineral Resources of the Midwestern
 US. pages 95–106, in: M D Lucas, R M Ross, & A N
 Swaby (eds.) The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth
 Science of the Midwestern US Paleontological
 Research Institution, Ithaca, New York
- Wall, AF, 2014, Topography of the Midwestern US. pages 85–94, in: M D Lucas, R M Ross, & A N Swaby (eds.) The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth Science of the Midwestern US Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York
- Wall, AF and Allmon, WD, 2014, Fossils of the Midwestern US. Pages 57–83, in: MD Lucas, RM Ross, & AN Swaby (eds.) The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth Science of the Midwestern US Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York
- Wall, AF and Parish, JT, 2014, Climate of the Midwestern US. pages 165–180, in: MD Lucas, RM Ross, & AN Swaby (eds.) The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth Science of the Midwestern US Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York
- Allmon, WD; Kissel, RA; and Wall, AF, 2015, Fossils of the South Central US. pages 81-138 in: MD Lucas, RM Ross, & AN Swaby (eds.), The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth Science of the South Central US Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York.

Grants Awarded

- In support of "Taphonomic lag on land: Snail death assemblages show rapid incorporation of synanthropic living communities on San Salvador Island, The Bahamas":
 - ★ February 3, 2015 The Paleontological Society Scholarship: \$900 USD
- In support of "Bellwether of the Canaries: Anthropogenic effects on the land snail fauna of the Canary Islands":
 - ★ April 3, 2015 Geological Society of America Research Grant, \$1875 USD
 - ★ April 20, 2015 Society of Sedimentary Geology Student Research Grant, \$800 USD
 - ★ May 19, 2015 Conchologists of America Academic Grant, \$2290 USD

Publications (cont)

- Kissel, RA and Wall, AF, 2014, <u>Geologic History of the Midwestern US.</u> pages 19-34 in: M D Lucas, R M Ross, & A N Swaby (eds.), *The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Geology of the Midwestern US* Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York.
- Kissel, RA and Wall, AF, 2014, Rocks of the Midwestern US. pages 35-56 in: M D Lucas, R M Ross, & A N Swaby(eds.), The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Geology of the Midwestern US Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York.
- Kissel, RA and AF Wall, 2015, Geologic History of the South Central US. pages 19-44 in: M D Lucas, R M Ross, & A N Swaby (eds.), The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth Science of the South Central US Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York.
- Kissel, RA, and Wall, AF, 2015, Topography of the South Central US. pages 139-166 in: MD Lucas, RM Ross, & AN Swaby (eds.), The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth Science of the South Central US Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York.
- Kissel, RA, and Wall, AF, 2016, <u>Topography of the Southwestern US.</u> In: MD Lucas, RM Ross, & AN Swaby (eds.), The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth Science of the Southwestern US. Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York.
- Mcann, L; Moore, A; Wall, AF; Lewis, G; and Parrish, JT, 2015, Soils of the Western US. pages 227-253 in: MD Lucas, RM Ross, & AN Swaby (eds.), The Teacher-Friendly Guide to the Earth Science of the Western US. Paleontological Research Institution, Ithaca, New York.